this is soliciting samhita nakiya 36:6
because a nun instructor were linked the
petitioner feels a pleasant feeling
feels a painful feeling and kills ain't
neither painful nor Pleasant feelings
pickers and instructed noble disciple in
area feels a pleasant feeling feels a
painful feeling and feels a neither
painful nor Pleasant feelings so because
what is the distinction then what is the
disparity what is the difference between
the Aria and a particular between a
noble disciple and a Warland
in because both feel the three types of
feeling but what is the difference
between those different individuals so
then the Munsell bantha teaching the
roots in the buddha so please please
explain so then the Buddha continues
because a nun instructed ordinary person
in being touched by painful feeling his
sorrows he's troubled he laments beats
his breast
cries becomes bewildered he feels two
feelings bodily and mental suppose
because a man was shot by an arrow he
would be shot in the wound by a second
arrow in this way because the man feels
the feeling of two arrows in just this
way and uninstructed worldly ordinary
person being touched by a painful
feeling sorrows his trouble lemons beat
his breast cries becomes confused he
feels two feelings bodily mental
so here the point it's quite important
is the distinguishing between bodily
mental feeling there's a common
assumption that a bodily feeling is
basically what people regarded bodily
sensations and so on like things you you
perceive in your body they are
uncomfortable and so on but that's
that's completely not the case
the Buddha said himself every feeling is
mental Chetta Sokka every feeling is is
basically felt on the level of the mind
so what is then how then should be
should we understand the bodily feeling
well if it says it says quite clearly
bodily feeling is anything any feeling
that you experience mentally on account
of things that you can perceive with
your body or within your body so
basically anything on account of your
sixth sense base so literally any
feeling that you have on account of a
site is about freely feeling a reason on
the bodily level now if you start
grieving further on account of that site
and in lamenting and and falling into
despair that's now the second feeling
that's further mental so bodily and
mental are both mental in a sense of
both felt with a mind but difference is
where they came from
so to speak so any bodily feeling is any
discomfort you will perceive by the body
or any comfort if you perceive by the
body internally or externally or both
it's not just for the internal things
you perceive in the body nor is it just
for the external things that you
perceive with the body it's both so if
you have if you have if you're
experiencing feelings on account of any
of the sense and you have the sense
objects whether it's sight sound smell
taste touch anything you've seen heard
and so on if there is a feeling of
reason on that account there is a bodily
feeling now both petitioner and an aria
would be experiencing that type of
bodily feeling and for that matter in a
way but we'll see that later our hand
also experience while bodily feeling but
you wouldn't call it a feeling if you
choose the word feeling to be applicable
to the feeling that you know as per to
Gina so the complete absence of what Regina's
so the complete absence of what Regina's
feeling then you can understand what
Aaron's feeling is but as I said that's
maybe a different
so now the difference between an aria
and between a puta Gina the the worldly
ordinary uninstructed person he stables
experience these feelings on account of
the senses internally externally
internally and externally but the
difference is - - Gina mentally has no
escape from that feeling which is why he
will always have pretty much a second
feeling on account of it simultaneously
present there so in account of the the
discomfort the pain touched through
touching you through the senses
something you've seen her taste that you
don't like that frightens you and so on
when a ton of that discomfort you will
be suffering mentally simultaneously
with it so that's what means you hit by
one arrow and immediately basically the
second arrow would shoot you in the
wound
so furthermore a nun instructed worldly
person being touched by painful feeling
he will feel a repulsion repelled by
this painful feeling the underlying
tendency to repulsion lies behind us
being touched by painful feeling he
delights in the pleasure sent his eyes
for what reason because because the
uninstructed whirling does not
understand any other escape from painful
feeling other than the pleasure of sense
desires so it just continues
so having experienced something that
pressures you through your senses you're
experiencing discomfort not knowing the
escape from the discomfort you start
experiencing mental anguish on account
of it not knowing the escape from their
mental anguish you then the only thing
you know is turn back to the same senses
that calls you that mental anguish and
just look for things that are Pleasant
in them and try to replace the
displeasing things with pleasing things
and that's that definition of sensuality
and sensual craving so that's this is
the further this passage further modest
just basically sheds more light on how
that bodily feeling should be understood
as I said it's not random sensations or
things you perceive on account of a
sense of touch of your body
it's basically feeling
you're experiencing on account of things
that you perceive three of senses which
is why exactly but not knowing escape
from that you would turn back to the
same sense objects just trying to
replace them with with those that are
agreeable so because the because because
the uninstructed Odin a person does not
understand escape from painful feeling
other day the pleasure of sense desires
that's why for him the lighting in the
pleasure of sense desires then the
underlying tendency of passion towards
pleasant feeling lies behind us he
doesn't understand as it is the origin
the gratification a danger and escape of
those feelings for him not understanding
as it is it is the origin the
gratification the danger inescapable
those feelings the underlying tendency
of ignorance regarding either pain from
the present feeling lies behind us so if
he feels a pleasant feeling he feels
connected to it as it he's bound by it
if he feels a painful feeling he's bound
by it he feels neither painful nor
Pleasant feeling he feels bound by it so
this bhikkhus is called a nun instructed
only person who's connected who is bound
by birth aging death sorrow lamentation
pain grief despair unhappiness trouble
who is bound with suffering I say so
just to just to recap a pagina feels the
feelings that have arisen on account of
his body on account of things and when
you say body
you mean sixth sense base that's what
what is you know the body because of the
six senses and you know the sixth sense
is because there is a unit called body
did they basically consist of so footage
and experiences of feeling on account of
anything that can come through his
senses but it's a sense of touch like
uncomfortable bodily sensations like I
don't know rough stone you have to sleep
on heat called or even if it's something
like a displeasing sight frightening
sound a disagreeable disgusting taste horrible
a disagreeable disgusting taste horrible
smell
any of these things that you will be
perceiving there on the level of
perception they do cause you
simultaneously to be pressured by an
unpleasant feeling in regard to it
it's disagreeable you feel it
unpleasantly and there is absolutely no
problem with this if then if you J would
know the escape of it if he would
understand the impermanence of the sense
base is the the impossibility the
inherent lack of ownership of your own
body like fully understood that not just
occasionally thought about it it would
be impossible for him well he won't be a
petitioner but it would be impossible
for him to be pressured by any feeling
they would arise in regard to that which
has been understood as completely
impermanent impossible to own cannot
pertain to you cannot bother you in that
sense but by not understanding that he
gets hit by the second arrow of pain so
notice that you're pressured but then
you recognize that you have absolutely
no means of escape from that pressure of
that painful feeling because literally
you can't shut down if you mean you can
pull your eyes out and still you can
suffer on account of absence of vision
now whatever the visual domain remains
the senses remain intact even if you
start try to destroy them
and that's when those people back back
in the day said to the Buddha or they
practice by not seeing things and not
hearing things with their ears and not
seeing things with their eyes and says
you're not different in a blind and the
Deaf man there's no wisdom in that
you're just avoiding because you don't
know where the problem is so not knowing
where the problem is you don't know the
escape from the problem you then suffer
twice as much so to speak so there is
suffering on account of simple disagree
ability of certain sense experience so
bodily suffering you can call it but
then because not knowing the escape
there is the mental suffering involved
literally think of it like this so
there's something bothering you
physically say but there is also a
possibility a certain prospect within
that thing the
might be life-threatening so in itself
it's it's not impossible to endure that
certain discomfort you could endure it
but there is a thought attached to it
that this actually might be causing the
ending of your life might kill you so
then the significance even of that which
you could bear is now far worse because
you don't know the escape from it you
don't know how to prevent it and your
life is at stake
and that's the real suffering here it's
not that discomfort on account of body
body the feeling that you're
experiencing it's that mental anguish on
account of not knowing the escape and
recognizing that well if it doesn't
crush you now it will at some point in
the future that's why but I said by
being bound to those feelings that have
a reason on account of sense organs of
your body you abandoning aging death
despair you're bound by samsara you're
bound by the whole thing
so that's the real problem not knowing
this scape is where the dukkha is and
which is why exactly for sotapanna he
becomes a sort of money becomes an area
by knowing the escape from Duke the Four
Noble Truths is a definition of escape
from the ducati has been understood so
then the same puto Gina who now has this
mental anguish and by the way even the
agreeable pleasure the touches your body
it still crushes you it still felt on
the level of that bodily feeling it's
felt unpleasant we cover that in other
talks you can I think if you look at the
what is it the sensual overcome a
sensuality playlist it's all there but
the point is that even the seemingly
agreeable prospect of central
gratification it's first felt
unpleasantly at this suit that repeats
that so if anything fell through the
body crushes you bothers you so to speak
like the the simile of the fluid cow
whichever way you lean or experience is
going to be bothersome now no in the
escape you get the mental anguish on
account of it not knowing the escape
from there
you then turn back the only direction
you know which is the direction of the
senses that cause the whole thing so
that's the irony of the whole central
craving because sensuality is painful
you seek it in order to overcome that
pain in order to basically replace that
pain you seek that which causes the pain
that's what we the compared central
attachment to madness
so the petitioners technically are mad
because it's it's it's the level of
madness or gave the other simulates like
a burning yourself with the burning the
coil car coal so the embers burning your
skin because it offers you some sort of
numbing gratification of your sort of
itchy itchy disease and so on so not
knowing the escape from their discomfort
you turn back to the very thing that
caused you their discomfort and then
just try to seek less uncomfortable
things which is what sensual it is since
Charlotte is not actually Pleasant
sentient is simply less painful from
other more painful things in less pain
from the perspective of pain especially
if you want to get rid of the pain he's
to be gonna be seen as it as pleasant as
extremely wanted and welcomed so that's
what we the means by by pathogen and not
understanding is any escape from painful
feeling any other escape then the
pleasure of the sense desires he goes
for the pleasure of sense desires that's
why he cultivates the delight so next
time anything uncomfortable touches him
he simultaneously his mind is in the
inner state of a context basically that
values escape from that discomfort
through sensuality so simply by
experiencing discomfort
he already delights in comfort even if
he's not necessarily seeking it the mind
will hold the values of comfort so he'll
be delighting in it and that's what we
refers to this underlying tendencies so
you need to stop the lighting in comfort
and stop the lighting you're trying to
get rid of the pain so then he goes on
this with the carries on and
about the re Osaka the instructor novel
disciple when he's touched by painful
feeling he does not sorrow he's not
troubled he doesn't lament so now why wouldn't he
he doesn't lament so now why wouldn't he
not sorrow
what's the difference well the
difference is he understood the the
implicit did the thoroughly thoroughly
understood the implicit impermanence of
that an account of which feelings have
arisen and that's important to say you
got oh she understood feelings are
oh she understood feelings are
impermanent new he understood that too
by proxy but you need to understand as
the Buddha would say well that because
of which feelings are the origin of
feeling so you need to understand the
that ordered is impermanent left alone
then the feeling that has a reason on
account of it so it's not just a
question of repeating to yourself there
whatever you're currently feeling all
this is impermanent it's not mine it's
not mine I can own and there is no sense
of control
that's just management on account of you
already being bothered by the feeling
you want to see through that presently
enduring feeling see what it depends on
so you realize whatever take a pleasant
or unpleasant feeling say in this case
unpleasant feeling on account of so you
touched by something painful so mentally
you touched by pain on account of I
don't know seeing seeing somebody you
really dislike somebody that hurt you in
the past or something like that
somebody had ill will towards so just
the mere sight of that person on the
street and you're experiencing mental
pain so you don't want to now just be
trying to get rid of that pain or
explain to something that pain is
impermanent you want to see that your
eyes are impermanent like would you be
able to experience that feeling if there
were no sight whatsoever impossible he
was on account of sight and he requires
your memory of the same sight it's
impossible it's still within the site
domain but now are you in the position
to choose what sites will arise for you
what sites will not arise for you what
sounds you like sometimes you can access
as some sense of control but overall
which is more times you've seen things
you couldn't see you didn't want to see
or times you seen things you want to see
it's far more
things you don't want to see things you
didn't plan of seen maybe you decided
you want to see them later but the point
is you have no say in your eyes seeing
or not seeing it's not up to you not
dwelling sufficiently enough of that
direct recognition that's how you
basically start appropriate in your eyes
in your sights which is why then you get
pressures on account of feelings that
arise on account of sights but if you
don't forget that you're all very eyes I
know cannot be yours even if you want
them to because if they could be yours
they would an age they would be liable
to sickness accidents and so on they
would never stop working but they're
clearly not yours so they just keep
providing you with this content of sites
and same goes for another organ and you
just keep taking it up all for granted
as if it you created it as is dead
because of you so that's the
impermanence that needs to be dead state
that's the level of furniture Sankara on
Nietzsche not dominate you because when
you are concerned about your feeling
thinking about present feeling at that
moment that is the dumb of your
experience so you want to see the same
card of that Dhamma as other suitors say
Sabah sankhara Nietzsche sabi sankhara
dukkhata be dominate so this feeling
it's going to be seen is not self when
you see that that upon which that
feeling depends is impermanent and
uncomfortable not pleasant not worth
owning so that's what an instructor
noble disciple has understood he is
understood in this particular example
the extent of of the body and any
feeling that can arise on account of the
body and when I say the extent I mean
the extent the nature of the
characteristics he cannot be owned so it
becomes inconceivable for him to grieve
on account of that which cannot it's
just it's impossible to even imagine the
ownership of it the only reason people
still keep imagining the ownership of
the senses is because they never make
sufficient amount of effort to think it
through correctly that it cannot beyond
and then any effort that's made it's
usually made then on the level of the
feeling our feelings on mind feelings
and if you're feeling the nature
feeling bothers you but that's not the
right level you need to see through that
feeling that which because of which the
feeling is so understanding that sin
Cara's are impermanent that's that's
what that statement means so because an
aria being attached by painful feeling
he doesn't sorrow is not trouble does
not lament does not be beat she's
dressed there's not try and does not
become confused he feels only one
feeling on account of the body North
mental suppose because a man was shocked
by narrow he would be he would not be
shot in the wound by a second arrow in
this way because the man feels the
feeling of one arrow in just this way
because a nun instructor noble disciple
being touched by painful feeling does
not sorrow he's not troubled does not
lament does not beat his breast does not
cry and does not become confused he
feels one feeling and a kind of body not
on account of his mind and for him being
touch but painful feeling there isn't
there is no repulsion so there is no
aversion towards that painful feeling
which is any feeling that at that level
any feeling is pressuring you thus any
feeling is painful feeling but he's not
averse to pain because he doesn't need
to be a hit why would he want to be rid
of the pain when he knows that it's not
his concern
he hasn't created it he has a reason on
its own and he has understood that
whatever arises on its own that's why it
cannot it has to pass it has to come to
knit so there is nothing for him he
cannot think all this will last forever
and bother me forever which is usually
that the rational thought of all this
this pain would be forever even people
know they want he won't be there forever
they can't help but keep thinking it'll
be forever so I must get rid of it
just this once I must get rid of it and
then later on all contemplated won't be
forever well in Aria cannot think that
any more because she's fully understood
that whatever has the nature arising
that's why has netted to cease so when
he started by painful feeling he has no
well it's impossible for him to be
averse towards it so not being averse
towards this painful feeling the
underlying tendency towards a version
does not lie behind this so being
touched by painful feeling he doesn't
delight then in pleasure of sense
desires so if he is not then touched by
that second pain why would he then need
to try to get rid of it when it's not
there so when it's not there means the
basis for wanting sense pleasures is not
there for what reason the instructor noble
for what reason the instructor noble
disciple understands the escape from
painful feeling other than the pleasure
of sense desires so for him not
delighting in the pleasure of sense
desires the underlying tendency of
passion towards pleasant feeling does
not lie behind this he understands as it
is the origin the gratification the
danger and the escape of those feelings
we covered in other talks what the
origin is what the gratification mother
danger the escape is you might search a
channel for him the understanding as it
is from for him understanding as it is
the origin the gratification the danger
and the escape from these feeling the
underlying tendency towards ignorance
regarding neither pain from the present
feeling does not live behind this if he
feels pleasant feeling he feels it on
unconnected to it so he's not bound by
it if he feels a painful feeling he is
not bound by it if he feels neither
painful nor Pleasant feeling he is not
bound by it this because is called an
unstructured noble and instructed sorry
an instructor noble disciple who is
unconnected unbound by birth aging death
sorrow lamentation pain and happiness
trouble he is unbound by suffering this
because is the distinction this is the
disparity this is the difference between
uninstructed noble disciple and
uninstructed ordinary person one with
understanding does not feel a feeling
pleasant painful one who has learned
much between the wise clever one and the
ordinary person this is the big
difference for one who is recognized the
Dhamma one who has learned much seeing this
one who has learned much seeing this
world and the next things are wished for
to notice the things that are wished for
to not disturb the mind and things
basically they're not wished for do not
repel the mind
so for him welcoming or opposing are
extinguished brought an end to not exist
having understood the stainless odorless
place the one who is gone beyond being
understands these things correctly